In March 1970, an election was held in
the small town of Bridgewater in
Somerset.
>> This is your opportunity to meet Tom
King, your Conservative candidate now.
It was a by-election held following the
death of the town's MP, Gerald Wills.
This election would be different. See,
the year before the government had
passed the Representation of the People
Act 1969. This lowered the minimum
voting age in the UK from 21 to 18. I
think that
in 1970 it probably makes some sense.
>> It was a far less controversial move
than you might think. Some veterans
under the age of 21 had briefly been
granted the right to vote in the wake of
the First World War. The 1960s had also
seen a wave of youth protest and
political movements which made ignoring
the voices of 18- to 21-year-olds more
and more difficult to justify. The
change was part of a global trend. The
following year, Canada also extended the
vote to 18, 19, and 20-year-olds.
[music] The year after that, the United
States and the Netherlands did the same.
Today, it would be easier to list the
countries in which the voting age isn't
18 than those in which it is. I won't.
That would be a really boring video.
>> When the Labour Party under Keir Starmer
was elected in 2024, one of the pledges
contained in their manifesto was to go
one step further and reduce the voting
age once again to 16. Is granting
16-year-olds and 17-year-olds the right
to vote a step too far, or does it have
the potential to inject new energy into
our politics at a time when democracy
across the world is under threat?